Guide to the Charles E. Scriven collection on Brooklyn history 1973.254
Brooklyn Historical Society
Charles E. Scriven collection on Brooklyn history
circa 1900 to 1937
1905-1907
Brooklyn Historical Society
Scriven, Charles E.
1973.254
0.63 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and one half manuscript box.
The Charles E. Scriven collection on Brooklyn history spans the period circa 1900 to 1937 and is comprised of materials either written or compiled by Scriven (1848?-1936) in the course of documenting the history of Brooklyn from the colonial period up to the early 20th century, with particular emphasis on the neighborhood of Flatbush.
Biographical Note
Charles E. Scriven (1848?-1936) was a printer whose business, Charles Scriven and Co., was located at 74 Beekman Street in Manhattan. Scriven lived at 149 Snyder Avenue in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Flatbush, and was involved in Flatbush civic life, serving as Recording Secretary of the Flatbush Taxpayers' Association and as Past High Priest of the Flatbush Chapter of the Royal Arch Masons. Scriven was also a local historian who extensively documented the history of Brooklyn, with particular emphasis on Flatbush.
Source: "Charles E. Scriven." New York Times, December 30, 1936.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Scope and Contents
The Charles E. Scriven collection on Brooklyn history spans the period circa 1900 to 1937 and is comprised of materials either written or compiled by Scriven in the course of documenting the history of Brooklyn from the colonial period up to the early 20th century, with particular emphasis on the neighborhood of Flatbush. Materials include typed original essays and transcriptions of articles and essays from various sources; news clippings; correspondence; and ephemera relating to a wide range of subjects such as banking, churches, civic organizations, government, homesteads, landmarks, libraries, public schools, public transit, public utilities, and realty development. Specific subjects strongly represented include the consolidation of New York City in 1898, Erasmus Hall High School, the Flatbush Carnegie Library (later the Flatbush branch of the Brooklyn Public Library), the Flatbush Taxpayers' Association, Melrose Hall homestead, the Prison Ship Martyrs' Monument in Fort Greene Park, and the public water supply, among many others.
There are also numerous references to African Americans in Brooklyn, including a transcription of an article from The Rural concerning an investigation into the murder of an African American in 1872. This article is located in the folder "Clippings - General Brooklyn interest."
A small portion of the collection expands its focus beyond Brooklyn and relates to the history of the greater New York City area, such as papers on the origins of New York City street names and news clippings containing items of citywide historical interest.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick Heyer, 1937.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related materials:
- Flatbush Taxpayers' Association records (1977.212), 1896-1914
- In stage coach days by Charles E. Scriven (974.722 S43), 1915
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Citizens' associations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public utilities -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Dwellings -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Libraries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Real property -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Politics and government; Banks and banking -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; New York (N.Y.) -- History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Annexation (Municipal government) -- New York (State) -- New York; Monuments -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public Schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Water-supply -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Prison Ship Martyrs' Monument (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History; Local histories; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Printed ephemera; Flatbush Carnegie Library (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Melrose Hall (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Scriven, Charles E.; Flatbush Taxpayers' Association (New York, N.Y.)
- Banking, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- [Carnegie] library, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Churches, 1902-1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings - General Brooklyn interest, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Clippings of General New York City interest, 1905-1913 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Consolidation, 1907-1909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- [Cris Deven, Church Avenue Lake], 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Dan Curran, Adam Balzer, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- [Dankers and Sluyter transcript], circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Development, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Erasmus Hall High School, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Flatbush from Dr. Strong's history, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Flatbush Taxpayers Association, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- From Stiles' History of Long Island, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- [Gravesend news clippings], 1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- [Hudson-Fulton celebration news clippings], 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- J. J. Snyder in re: historic house, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Landmarks, 1909-1916 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Landmarks of Old New York, Origins of Street Names in New York, circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Melrose Hall, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- [Poetry], circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Reminiscences of Flatbush, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Schools, 1904-1913 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
- [Thomas Paine, New Rochelle], 1905-1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Transit, 1906-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Water, 1905-1937 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)